معراتة، قرية سورية جميلة تتبع مركز مدينة عفرين
Ma'rata, a beautiful Syrian village belonging to the center
of Afrin city
وتقع إلى الغرب منها بخمسة كيلومترات.
and located five kilometers to the west of it.
كما أنها تبعد عن مدينة حلب خمسة وستين كيلومتراً باتجاه
الشمال الغربي.
It is also 65 kilometers northwest of the city of Aleppo.
بنيت بيوت القرية بشكل متصاعد من الأسفل نحو الأعلى، فوق سفحي
هضبتين جبليتين متقابلتين،
The houses of the village were built in an ascending manner
from the bottom to the top, on the slopes of two facing
mountains,
يفصلهما وادٍ تمر فيه مياه نبعة ماء تسقي أراضي القرية.
separated by a valley through which the water of a spring
flows, watering the lands of the village.
يبلغ عدد سكان القرية ثلاثة آلاف وخمسمائة نسمة، من الأكراد
والعرب السوريين،
The population of the village is 3,500 people, of Syrian
Kurds and Arabs,
إضافة إلى المهجرين من مناطق سورية مختلفة، وخاصة أرياف حلب
وحماة والرقة وإدلب.
in addition to displaced people from different Syrian
regions, especially the countryside of Aleppo, Hama, Raqqa,
and Idlib.
يعتمد أهلها بشكل أساسي في معيشتهم على الزراعة، وخاصة زراعة
الزيتون والحبوب بأنواعها، وعلى تربية المواشي والوظائف
العامة.
Its people depend mainly on agriculture for their
livelihood, especially the cultivation of olives and grains
of all kinds, as well as raising livestock and public jobs.
ترتفع فيها نسبة حاملي الشهادات الجامعية من كافة التخصصات،
ويوجد فيها مدرستين ابتدائية وإعدادية.
The percentage of university degree holders in all
specializations is high, and there are two primary and
middle schools in it.
يغلب عليها الطابع الزراعي المتمدن، ويتميز أهلها بحبهم للعلم
والعمل معاً.
The civilized agricultural character prevails over it, and
its people are distinguished by their love for both
knowledge and work together.
الله يعطيك العافية أبو رمزي.
May God give you health, Abu Ramzi.
الله يعافيك، أهلاً وسهلاً أخي، شرفتونا، أنتم بقناة حلب
اليوم.
May God give you health, welcome brother, you honored us,
you are Halab Today channel.
الله يكرمك. هلا أبو رمزي، أنا لاحظت يعني خلال إعدادي للجولة
في الضيعة في معراتة،
May God honor you. Now Abu Ramzi, I noticed during my
preparation for the tour in the village in Ma'rata,
إنه في انتشار واسع للبزق في الضيعة. يعني مثلاً إنت وأخوك
بتعزفوا، حسب ما فهمت.
that there is a widespread presence of the buzuq in the
village. For example, you and your brother play, as I
understood.
والله عندنا من زمان، وعائلتنا بشكل عام يعني بحبوا الفن، يعني
الموسيقى بشكل عام.
Well, we have had it for a long time, and our family in
general loves art. I mean, music in general.
تمام، لكن يعني حب البزق والموسيقى مرتبط بطبيعة الضيعة
الحلوة؟
Great, but is the love for the buzuq and music related to
the beautiful nature of the village?
إيوا، بالجبال، بالطبيعة، بالبحر، بكل شيء. يعني الموسيقى بشكل
عام بحب يعني بالطبيعة، جو طبيعة.
Yes, to the mountains, the nature, the sea, to everything. I
mean, music in general loves nature, a natural atmosphere.
طيب، هلا أنت اللي عزفتوا، شو عزفت؟
Alright, what you just played now, what did you play?
تقسيم هذا كردي، لمحمد علي تجو الله يرحمه، ويرحم أمواتكم
كمان.
This is a Kurdish taqsim, by Muhammad Ali Tajo, may God have
mercy on him, and have mercy on your dead ones too.
تعيش. يعني فلكلور غنائي كردي بالمنطقة؟
May you live. So it's Kurdish vocal folklore in the region?
كردي، تركي، عربي كمان، عندنا كل شيء. كل شيء.
Kurdish, Turkish, and Arabic too, we have everything.
Everything.
هلا إذا بدنا نسمع شيء خاص خاص بمعراتة وما حولها، شو بدك
تسمعنا؟
Now, if we want to hear something very specific to Ma'rata
and its surroundings, what would you play for us?
يعني موسيقى، يعني شيء غني غريب يعني؟
You mean music, like a strange rich piece?
إي يعني، يعني بدي شيء ارتجالي من روح... من روح المنطقة، روح
الطبيعة هيك، وروح السكان اللي هون.
Yes, I mean, I want something improvisational from the
spirit... from the spirit of the region, the spirit of
nature, and the spirit of the residents here.
كردي عربي ما في فرق؟
Doesn't matter if it's Kurdish or Arabic?
لا، ما في مشكلة. لأن هون في كرد وعرب.
No, there's no problem. Because there are Kurds and Arabs
here.
أيوا الحمد لله، لا الحمد لله ما في يعني تفرقة.
Right, thank God, there is no, thank God there is no
discrimination.
إي لذلك سمعني هذا... هذا المزاج العام الكردي العربي اللي
هون.
Yes, that's why play for me this... this general Kurdish-
Arabic mood that is here.
عادي ما في مشكلة. أهلاً وسهلاً أخي. تفضل.
Normal, no problem. Welcome brother. Go ahead.
يا سلام، يا سلام، الله يعطيك العافية.
Oh wow, oh wow, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك، أهلاً وسهلاً أخي.
May God give you health, welcome brother.
كنت عم بحس، كنت عم بحس إنه في أكتر... يعني بصراحة أكتر من
بزق عم بدق، أكتر من آلة عم تعزف،
I was feeling, I was feeling that there is more... honestly,
more than one buzuq playing, more than one instrument
playing,
مو بس بزق، كأنه في آلات أخرى عم تعزف، من كتر ما شاء الله
عليك ما إنت محترف وعم بتجيد العزف.
not just a buzuq, as if there are other instruments playing,
because, mashallah, you are so professional and master the
playing.
السؤال اللي بدي أسألك ياه، سؤالين عندي سريعات، شو قالت
الأوتار تبعك؟ شو كانت عم بتقول؟
The question I want to ask you, I have two quick questions.
What did your strings say? What were they saying?
البزق؟
The buzuq?
إي، أنت شو كنت عم تحكي حكي بدون صوت؟
Yes, what were you saying without a voice?
إي في حكي من جوات القلب. إي وقت إنت عم بتدق البزق يعني في
أغنية، في كلمات من جوات القلب.
Yes, there are words from inside the heart. When you play
the buzuq, there's a song, there are words from inside the
heart.
شو قلت إنت بجوات قلبك؟
What did you say inside your heart?
على المحبة، على الطبيعة، على كل شيء، عم بطلع معك، بس شو مخفي
هذا.
About love, about nature, about everything, it comes out
with you, but this is hidden.
يعني مرتك ما عم تسمعك هلق؟
So your wife is not hearing you right now?
لا أعوذ بالله هههه.
No, God forbid, haha.
الله يعطيك العافية يا ابو رمزي.
May God give you health, Abu Ramzi.
شكرا لك، يا هلا وسهلا، شرفتنا اخي ابو عراسي.
Thank you, welcome, you honored us, brother Abu Arasi.
السلام عليكم. الله يعطيك العافية.
Peace be upon you. May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health.
نتعرف عليكي؟
Can we get to know you?
اسمي ابنوري.
My name is Ibnouri.
اهلا وسهلا، من معراتة؟
Welcome, are you from Maarate?
كنت جاية زيارة لعند قرايبنا.
I just came to visit our relatives.
يا اهلا وسهلا فيكي. خلينا نحكي معك شوي.
You are very welcome. Let's talk with you a bit.
احكيلي عن الضيعة، احكيلي عن وضع المرأة في الضيعة.
Tell me about the village, tell me about the situation of
women in the village.
يعني كيف عايشين هون الناس؟ انتي عندك اولاد اكيد؟
I mean, how do people live here? You surely have children?
عندي اولاد ايه عندي.
I have children, yes I do.
وعندك زوجك. كيف عايشين؟ احكيلي كيف حياتكم؟
And you have a husband. How do you live? Tell me, how is
your life?
عايشين والله عادي. عايشين عاديين يعني ما في شي.
We live a normal life, honestly. We live normally, there's
nothing out of the ordinary.
شو بتشتغلوا؟
What do you do for work?
زوجي بيشتغل مزارع.
My husband works as a farmer.
مزارع؟
A farmer?
وانا ربة بيت.
And I am a housewife.
عندكم ارض؟
Do you have land?
عندنا الحمد لله.
We have, thank God.
تمام. واولادك عم بيتعلموا؟
Great. Are your children getting an education?
اولادي لا، تعليم ما في. ما في مدارس.
No, my children aren't getting an education. There are no
schools.
انا بعرف في مدرستين، ابتدائي واعدادي هون.
I know there are two schools, primary and middle here.
في اعدادي، بنتي بطلت، ما عاد في.
There is a middle school, my daughter dropped out, there is
no more.
ما في امان بعفرين، من هيك بطلناهم من المدارس.
There's no safety in Afrin, that's why we took them out of
school.
طيب، اسألك سؤال، احكيلي عن وضع المرأة هون.
Okay, let me ask you a question, tell me about the situation
of women here.
المرأة؟
Women?
ايه، باعتبارك انتي يعني سيدة. بكل شي، كيف حياتها هون؟
Yes, considering you are a lady. Everything, how is her life
here?
عادية، المرأة الموظفة بتروح بتداوم بوظيفتها،
Normal. An employed woman goes and attends her job,
المرأة اللي ست بيت بتضلها ست بيت ببيتها، ما في شي.
and a housewife stays a housewife in her home, nothing
special.
حسب ما فهمت انه في شهادات جامعية كتير من النساء هون،
From what I understand, there are many university degrees
among women here,
في محاميات، في طبيبات، في مهندسات، في معلمات...
there are female lawyers, doctors, engineers, teachers...
ايه اكيد، كاي مجتمع سوري، اكيد فيه.
Yes, certainly, like any Syrian society, there certainly
are.
يعني اذا قلت في ناس نازحين لهون، اكيد في دكاترة وكمان في...
I mean, if you say there are displaced people here, there
are certainly doctors and also...
يعني في شهادات عليا كمان.
I mean, there are higher degrees too.
شو الخاص بالمرأة في معراتة؟
What is specific to women in Maarate?
شو خاص بمعراتة؟ والله يعني...
What is specific to Maarate? Well, I mean...
ما بعرف شو... يعني حدد لي الشي.
I don't know what... specify it for me.
انا عم بسألك، انا عم بسألك، انا...
I am asking you, I am asking you, I...
مرأة عادية، عم اقول لك، ست البيت هي ببيتها،
Normal women, I'm telling you, a housewife is in her home,
والموظفة بتداوم بوظيفتها. اذا بدها بتروح، اذا ما بدها ما
بتروح، هيك يعني.
and an employed woman goes to her job. If she wants to she
goes, if she doesn't want to she doesn't go, like that.
شو اللي تغير بوضع المرأة بالفترة الاخيرة؟
What has changed in the situation of women recently?
تغير كتير. هلا ايام قبل الحرب شي وهلا شي تاني.
It has changed a lot. Now days before the war were one thing
and now it's another thing.
يعني تغيرت كتير اشياء، بس...
I mean, many things have changed, but...
يعني رغم هيك عايشين عاديين.
I mean, despite that, we live normally.
في مجتمع هون فيه حيوية؟
Is there a society with vitality here?
في معراتة؟ يعني الناس بتزور بعضها، في مناسبات، في افراح، في
كذا؟
In Maarate? I mean, do people visit each other, are there
events, weddings, things like that?
ايه ايه، بيعيشوا، بيعملوا افراح، بيعملوا اعراس، بيعملوا خطب،
يعني عادي.
Yes, yes, they live, they have celebrations, weddings,
engagements, it's normal.
بيعملوا زيارات كمان. حتى... يعني ما في عندنا هالـ...
They visit each other too. Even... I mean, we don't have
this...
اقصد انه الحياة تأثرت بالحرب ولا ما زالت فيها هالحيوية
الحلوة؟
I mean, has life been affected by the war, or does it still
have this beautiful vitality?
اذا قلت حرب، اكيد رح تتأثر الحياة، اكيد.
If you say war, life will certainly be affected, certainly.
بس مو هالتأثير الزايد، يعني رغم هيك العالم بدهم يعيشوا
حياتهم،
But not an excessive effect. I mean, despite that, people
want to live their lives,
يعني ما وقفت عالحرب.
I mean, it didn't stop because of the war.
تمام، تمام. في سؤال عم يخطر عبالي، هذا اللي حاطتيه ع راسك شو
هذا؟
Right, right. A question came to my mind, what is this thing
on your head?
هذا ايشارب.
This is a scarf.
ايشارب عادي ولا خاص بتراث المنطقة؟
A regular scarf or specific to the region's heritage?
لا لا، تراث المنطقة، هذا اللي عندي ياه من زمان كتير.
No, no, the region's heritage. I've had this one for a very
long time.
لونه اخضر مميز. وهذا اللباس الان، اللي...
Its green color is distinct. And these clothes now, that...
اللي بيلبسوه يعني السيدات الكرديات؟
that Kurdish women wear?
لا، هلا في منهم بيلبسوا فساتين، في منهم بيلبسوا تنانير،
No, now some wear dresses, some wear skirts,
في منهم بيلبسوا سبور، بناتنا بيلبسوا سبور.
some wear casual clothes, our girls wear casual clothes.
بس النسوان الاكبر مني بيلبسوا يا جلابية، يا فستان، يا تنورة،
او شي.
But women older than me wear either a jalabiya, a dress, a
skirt, or something.
يعني حسب كل واحد وشو بيلبس، ما في شي انه...
I mean, it depends on each person and what they wear, there
isn't anything that...
هلا هذا، هذا الشي انا اللي شايفه...
Now this, this thing what I see is...
كأنه يعني بيناسب طبيعة الضيعة؟
It's like it suits the nature of the village?
ايه.
Yes.
طبيعة تكوينها؟ انه زراعي متمدن؟
The nature of its composition? Being agricultural and
urbanized?
ايه هلا... المدينة كلها نزحت عالضيعة.
Yes, now... The whole city was displaced to the village.
يعني في منهم بيلبسوا بالضيعة، يعني بحكم الضيعة، انه مشان
السترة او كذا هيك،
I mean, some dress in the village, I mean, due to the
village, for modesty or things like that,
وفي منهم عادي. بيضلوا على طبيعتهم.
and some dress normally. They stay in their natural way.
الله يعطيك العافية، شكرا الك.
May God give you health, thank you.
الله يعافيك، شكرا كتير الكن.
May God give you health, thank you all so much.
على الرغم من الطابع الزراعي العام لمعراتة،
Despite the general agricultural nature of Maarate,
باعتبار اهالي القرية بيعيشوا من اراضيهم ومن تربية المواشي،
considering the village residents live off their lands and
raising livestock,
ولكن هذا ما بيمنع وجود ورشات صغيرة للخياطة وغيرها وغيرها.
this doesn't prevent the existence of small sewing workshops
and others.
فرضتها ظروف الهجرة المعاكسة من الريف الى المدينة، وظروف
الحرب الصعبة.
Imposed by the conditions of reverse migration from the
countryside to the city, and the difficult war conditions.
بهالفقرة رح نتعرف معكم على وحدة من هيدي الورش، ورش الخياطة،
In this segment, we will get to know one of these workshops,
a sewing workshop,
لنشوف وضعها وشو فرص العمل اللي بتأمنها،
to see its situation, what job opportunities it provides,
والدخل اللي بيعيشوا منه هالعمال. تابعونا.
and the income these workers live off of. Stay with us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And peace be upon you.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك، يا هلا.
May God give you health, welcome.
حضرتك صاحب الورشة؟
Are you the workshop owner?
نعم.
Yes.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
جلال مراد.
Jalal Murad.
يا هلا وسهلا اخ جلال.
Welcome, brother Jalal.
يا مية هلا.
A hundred welcomes.
احكيلي قديش عمر هالورشة؟
Tell me, how old is this workshop?
والله هالورشة تقريبا صارلنا فاتحينها 6 - 7 سنين تقريبا.
Well, we've had this workshop open for about 6 to 7 years.
بلشنا بمشروع صغير. كنت اشتغل صانع عند العالم، اول ما جينا...
We started with a small project. I used to work as an
apprentice for people when we first came...
جيتم من حلب لهون؟
You came from Aleppo to here?
جينا من حلب لهون.
We came from Aleppo to here.
لا، ما كان في ورشة. كنت اشتغل صانع عند العالم.
Did you have a workshop in Aleppo?
No, I didn't have a workshop. I worked as an apprentice for
people.
من بداية الاحداث يعني، صارت مشاكل بحلب كمان، انزمنا لهون
عالضيعة.
Since the beginning of the events, problems happened in
Aleppo too, so we fled here to the village.
انا اصلي من هون من الضيعة.
I am originally from here, from the village.
بلشت كمان اشتغل صانع هون عند العالم. يعني شوي شوي طورنا
حالنا شوي،
I also started working as an apprentice here for people. I
mean, step by step we improved ourselves a bit,
يعني اشتريت كم ماكينة، دبرت حالي شوي.
I mean, I bought a few machines, I managed a bit.
يعني الامور مشيت شوي، الحمد لله، وكبرناها شوي.
I mean, things moved forward a bit, thank God, and we
expanded it a little.
كان في ورشات هون سابقا؟
Were there workshops here previously?
كان بالضيعة في ورشات؟
Were there workshops in the village?
ما كان في ورشات طاولة. نحن اول ورشة فتحناها بالضيعة.
There were no workshops at all. We are the first workshop to
open in the village.
اول ورشة بتنفتح بالضيعة، تبعيتنا.
The very first workshop opened in the village is ours.
تمام. هلا كم فرصة عمل بتشغل هون؟
Great. Now, how many job opportunities do you provide here?
والله 10 تقريبا.
Well, about 10.
10؟ ان شاء الله في حركة؟
10? Is there good movement, hopefully?
الحمد لله. والله الحركة هلا هالجمعتين تلاتة في حركة.
Thank God. Well, these past two or three weeks there's been
movement.
بس من قبل كان ما في. خفيف، يعني نشتغل بالجمعة مثلا تلات اربع
ايام ونوقف يومين.
But before that, there wasn't. It was slow, I mean we'd work
three or four days a week and stop for two days.
بس هلا في حركة شوي، يعني ماشية الامور الحمد لله.
But now there's a bit of movement, I mean, things are going
okay, thank God.
تمام، تمام. شو المعوقات اللي عم بتواجهكم؟
Good, good. What are the obstacles you are facing?
والله المعوقات يا معلم، في غلا.
Well, the obstacles, boss, there are high prices.
الغلا، بالنسبة لـ... اهم شي المازوت.
High prices, especially for... the most important thing is
diesel.
المازوت اللتر هلا بيوقف علينا بـ 1350 لـ 1400، يعني غلا،
مشكلة كبيرة.
A liter of diesel now costs us between 1,350 to 1,400. I
mean, it's expensive, a big problem.
يعني باليوم عم بحسبها، اذا عم بشتغل 10 ساعات،
I mean, calculating it per day, if I work 10 hours,
عم بصرف تقريبا 20 الف مصروف للمولدة هادا بس.
I spend about 20,000 in expenses just for this generator.
مازوت وزيت وهادا... ما عدا التصليحات وهيك.
Diesel and oil and this... not to mention the repairs and
such.
ما عدا. ما في طاقة شمسية؟ ما في عندكم طاقة شمسية؟
Not to mention. Is there no solar energy? You don't have
solar energy?
والله في، انا ماني مركب. لو في امكانية اذا بركب اوفر لي.
Well, there is, but I haven't installed it. If it were
affordable to install, it would be cheaper for me.
او اذا بتجينا كهربا تركية لسه كمان اوفر. اوفر من المولدة
يعني.
Or if we get Turkish electricity, it would be even cheaper.
Cheaper than the generator, I mean.
طيب، خلينا نشوف الشباب اللي عندك كذا، نتعرف...
Okay, let's see the young men you have, let's get to know
them...
تفضل.
Go ahead.
اول شي بتشوف هالشاب؟
First thing, we see this young man?
والله الشباب كلهم من الضيعة عندي. جيراني، وهي مدامتي كمان.
Well, the young people are all from the village. My
neighbors, and this is my wife too.
يعني حتى مدامتي عم تيجي بتساعدني، لتمشي الامور يعني.
I mean, even my wife comes to help me, to keep things
moving.
بتعطيها اجرة ولا لا؟
Do you pay her a wage or not?
والله متل ما عم باخد هي كمان... انا وياها عم نعيش سوا يعني.
Well, just as I'm getting paid, she is too... we live
together, I mean.
طيب. مدام يعطيك العافية.
Okay. Madam, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
بدي احكي معك شوي.
I want to talk with you a bit.
اهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
تعرفي عليكي؟
Can we get to know you?
انا مرته لجلال مراد. بكون صاحب الورشة.
I am Jalal Murad's wife. He is the owner of the workshop.
اهلا وسهلا فيكي.
Welcome.
اهلين فيك.
Welcome to you.
بيعطيكي اجرة ولا بياخد اجرة الك؟
Does he pay you a wage or take a wage for you?
انا وياه، مالي وحاله واحد.
He and I, my money and his are one.
يا عيني عليكي. شو عندكم اولاد؟
Oh, my. Do you have children?
عندي اربع بنات.
I have four girls.
الله يخليهم يا رب.
May God protect them.
امين يا رب.
Amen.
عموما شلون ظروف العمل هون؟ متعبة؟ مرهقة؟ شلون؟
In general, how are the working conditions here? Tiring?
Exhausting? How?
طبعا، اكيد شي صعب. يعني...
Of course, it's definitely something difficult. I mean...
يعني كثير صعوبة كثير، مو قليل كمان. يعني عندي بيت وشغل، يعني
صعب.
I mean, a lot of difficulty, not a little bit either. I
mean, I have a home and a job, I mean, it's hard.
كم ساعة بتشتغلي هون؟
How many hours do you work here?
والله من الصبح بشتغل معه للمسا، هيك يوميا.
Well, I work with him from morning till evening, like this
daily.
يوميا.
Daily.
ايه.
Yes.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
خلينا نشوف غيرك باعتبارك انتي يعني زوجته رح ما تحكي عليه.
Let's see someone else, since you are his wife, you won't
speak ill of him.
ما رح ادعي عليه.
I won't pray against him.
طيب.
Okay.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And peace be upon you.
الحمد لله منيح.
How are you?
Good, thank God.
تعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
اهلا وسهلا يا مصطفى.
Mustafa.
Welcome, Mustafa.
شو هلا انت شو دورك هون في هالشغل هادا؟
What is your role here in this job?
والله هون انا بالورشة بشتغل، انا خياط يعني، بشتغل...
Well, here I work in the workshop, I'm a tailor, I work...
يعني في القطعة بتمر على شي 100 مرحلة، يعني بنشيلها.
I mean, the piece goes through about 100 stages, I mean we
carry it.
يعني مثلا اذا مو متلي، ومو متل الصانع اللي وراي، واللي غيره
وغيره، يعني الورشة ما بتمشي.
I mean, for example, if there isn't someone like me, and an
apprentice behind me, and others, the workshop doesn't run.
يعني بدوننا الورشة ما بتمشي. يعني مو بس يكون معلم.
I mean, without us, the workshop doesn't run. I mean, it's
not just about having a boss.
اصلا بده يكون يعني صوانع يكونوا موجودين. يعني اذا الصناع ما
يكونوا موجودين، الشغلة كلها ما بتمشي.
Essentially there have to be apprentices present. I mean, if
the apprentices aren't present, the whole thing doesn't run.
تمام. شقد اجرتك انت؟
Right. How much is your wage?
20 الف.
20,000.
بالجمعة؟
A week?
ايه بالجمعة 20 الف باخد.
Yes, a week, I take 20,000.
20 الف؟ كم ساعة باليوم؟
20,000? How many hours a day?
10 ساعات.
10 hours.
متزوج؟
Are you married?
لا، عزابي.
No, a bachelor.
من وين؟ من هالضيعة؟
Where from? From this village?
ايه نفس الضيعة انا.
Yes, the same village.
يعني ان شاء الله اموركم ماشية؟
So things are going well, hopefully?
الحمد لله يا رب. يعني الورشة اذا... بتشتغل الورشة، بيكون
فيه، الحمد لله كله تمام يعني.
Thank God. I mean, the workshop, if... if the workshop
works, there is [work], thank God, everything is fine.
بس يعني شوي المازوت غالي،
But diesel is a bit expensive,
يعني من حق المازوت كمان، يعني الحق العامل كمان عم ينزل.
I mean, because of the price of diesel, the worker's share
is also decreasing.
يعني اذا المازوت مو غالي، نحن يعني الرواتب كمان بترتفع.
I mean, if diesel weren't expensive, our salaries would also
rise.
يعني المازوت هيك عم يغلى، اجباري رح ينزل من الصانع.
I mean, diesel is getting expensive like this, inevitably it
will be taken from the apprentice.
يعني بينقص من اجرتكم؟
I mean, it reduces your wage?
ايه اجباري.
Yes, inevitably.
في كلفة كبيرة.
Because of the high cost.
ايه نعم.
Yes.
انت اشتغلت سابقا بهالمهنة؟
Did you work in this profession previously?
ايه.
Yes.
اشتغلت. وهلا هون عم بتكمل.
You did. And now you are continuing here.
وهون عم كمل.
And here I am continuing.
يا رب. الله يعطيك العافية.
Good. May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
اهلا وسهلا.
Thank you.
Welcome.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you all health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And peace be upon you, and God's mercy and blessings.
بمعراتة في علامات فارقة كثيرة بيعرفها القاصي والداني.
In Maarate, there are many distinct landmarks known to
everyone far and wide.
وما فيك تطلع من معراتة من دون ما تمر بهالضيعة:
And you can't leave Maarate without passing through this
village:
نبعة المي، المغارة الكبيرة،
The water spring, the big cave,
وشجرة البلوط المعمرة، اللي يمكن عمرها فوق الـ 150 سنة.
and the perennial oak tree, which might be over 150 years
old.
هلا نحن رايحين على نبعة المي.
Now we are going to the water spring.
اللي هي معلم اساسي من معالم معراتة متل ما قلنا.
Which is an essential landmark among the landmarks of
Maarate, as we said.
علامة فارقة، كل اللي بيشوفها بيتذكر العادات.
A distinct landmark, everyone who sees it remembers the
traditions.
وبيتذكر كيف كانت الناس تشرب من هالنبعة وكيف كانوا ايضا يسقوا
اراضيهم.
And remembers how people used to drink from this spring and
how they also watered their lands.
بيتذكر قطعان الاغنام والماعز اللي كانت تيجي لهون لحتى تشرب.
Remembers the flocks of sheep and goats that used to come
here to drink.
يا رب.
Oh God.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And peace be upon you.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك، اهلا وسهلا.
May God give you health, welcome.
اتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
إمام الضيعة، عبد المجيد هوسو.
The village Imam, Abdulmajeed Hoso.
يا اهلا وسهلا فيك.
Very welcome.
اهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
هلا نحن وين؟ عند النبعة؟
Now where are we? At the spring?
ع النبعة، الكبيرة.
At the spring, the big one.
في غيرها؟ اكثر من نبعة؟
Is there another one? More than one spring?
في... كانوا في نبعتين، هاي الكبيرة، والصغيرة صايرة جوات
الضيعة.
There are... there used to be two springs, this big one, and
the small one is inside the village.
الصغيرة نشفانة، بس هي لساتها على حالها.
The small one dried up, but this one is still as it was.
وين مكان النبعة هون بالضبط؟
Where is the exact location of the spring here?
مكان النبعة تحت الصبة هنيك بالضبط.
The location of the spring is right under the concrete slab
there.
شوية طرقاتنا وعرة، بدك تتحملنا. هات ايدك.
Our roads are a bit rugged, you have to bear with us. Give
me your hand.
هلا شيخي بس أنا بدي اسألك سؤال.
Welcome Sheikh, I just want to ask you a question.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
خلينا نمشي على طرف النبعة.
Let's walk to the edge of the spring.
طرف النبعة صار هنيك، قلب الوادي.
The edge of the spring is over there, in the heart of the
valley.
ايه خلينا نمشي على الوادي، الوادي.
Yes, let's walk to the valley, the valley.
هلا النبعة، مية النبعة مثل ما شايفينها...
Now the spring, the spring water as we can see it...
ايوه.
Yes.
تمشي في قلب الوادي.
It runs through the heart of the valley.
في قلب الوادي، بس من النقطة هداك عملنا ساتر،
In the heart of the valley, but from that point we made a
barrier,
مشان تتوزع عالطرفين، مشان الجماعة يستفيدوا منها
so it distributes to both sides, so the people can benefit
from it
يسقوا فيها خضروات، شجرات، كذا، كل شيء.
and water vegetables, trees, and everything else with it.
طيب أنا سؤالي إنه هيدي هي بتمشي في قلب الوادي اللي بيقسم
الضيعة قسمين؟
Okay, my question is, does it run through the heart of the
valley that divides the village into two parts?
قسمين، شمالي وجنوبي.
Two parts, northern and southern.
تمام، أيضاً كانت كل أراضي القرية بتنسقى من هالنبعة؟
Great. Also, were all the village lands watered from this
spring?
ببدايات، كانت الأمطار منيحة، حتى السهل، سهل الضيعة كان يسقوا
فيها،
In the beginnings, the rains were good, even the plain, the
village's plain was watered by it.
يعني مو ضيعة خاص فيها، حتى السهل كانوا يزرعوا فيها قطن،
I mean, not just the village specifically, even the plain,
they used to plant cotton in it,
يزرعوا فيها شوندر، كل شيء كان، كانت المي طافرة،
plant sugar beets in it, there was everything, the water was
overflowing.
هلق نفرض جدلاً هالمي تلاتة انش أو انشين، اعتبرها تلاتة،
Now let's assume this water is three inches or two inches,
consider it three,
بس بالبداية على حسب الأمطار، كانت تمشي فيها شي 15، 20 انش.
but in the beginning, depending on the rains, about 15 or 20
inches would flow through it.
يعني كانت تقضي وتوفي.
I mean, it was more than enough.
يعني هيدا المي بكرا مثلاً بالربيع بتعبي هالمجرى كلو؟
So this water, for example, tomorrow in the spring, it will
fill this whole stream?
لكان لكان لكان، يعني بداية الربيع، عرفت كيف؟
Of course, of course, of course, I mean at the beginning of
spring, you know?
هالكمية بتضاعف أضعاف. عرفت كيف؟
This amount multiplies many times over. You know?
يعني من انشين بتصل لـ 15 انش أو 20 انش.
I mean, from two inches, it reaches 15 inches or 20 inches.
وين بتصب المي؟
Where does the water flow into?
بتصب المي ع نهر عفرين.
The water flows into the Afrin River.
يعني الفائض...
So the surplus...
الفائض... هالوادي بتصل لنهر عفرين بالضبط.
The surplus... this valley reaches the Afrin River exactly.
تمام. ما شاء الله هلق هاي الطبيعة الحلوة كتير، طبيعة يعني
جميلة،
Great. Mashallah, now this is very beautiful nature, I mean
beautiful nature,
في أشجار، هيدي شجرة جوز؟
there are trees, is this a walnut tree?
شجرة جوز، ايوه شجرة جوز.
A walnut tree, yes, a walnut tree.
هلا في شجرة معروفة كمان بالضيعة كتير، شو اسمها؟ البلوط؟
الشجرة الكبيرة؟
Now there is also a very well-known tree in the village,
what's its name? The oak? The big tree?
ايه شجرة البلوط يمكن عمرها على ما أعتقد فوق الـ 500 سنة.
Yes, the oak tree, its age, I believe, is over 500 years.
500 سنة!
500 years!
فوق 500 سنة. يعني لو أربعتنا نلف ايدينا على بعض، عالجذع ما
بتنلف.
Over 500 years. I mean, if the four of us wrapped our arms
around each other, they wouldn't wrap around the trunk.
طيب احكيلي عن الذكريات وأهمية ذكريات هالنبعة بحياة الضيعة.
Well, tell me about the memories and the importance of the
memories of this spring in the life of the village.
أهمية النبعة بحياة الضيعة؟
The importance of the spring in the life of the village?
بالبداية، آبار ارتوازية كان ما في، مي موجودة، الاعتماد الكلي
على النبعة.
In the beginning, there were no artesian wells, water was
available, the total reliance was on the spring.
عالم بتيجي تسقي، تشرب، تسقي الدواب، بتغسل، حتى تتحمم فيها،
People would come to water, drink, water the animals, wash,
even bathe in it,
مثلاً كانت جوات الوادي، في مزراب،
for example, inside the valley, there was a spout,
كان أهل الضيعة كلياتهم يروحوا يتحمموا من تحت هداك المزراب.
عرفت كيف؟
all the village people used to go bathe under that spout.
You know?
المي من هون؟
The water is from here?
المي من هون. هي مي صحية 100%، يعني ما هي مي ملوثة.
The water is from here. It is 100% healthy water, I mean,
it's not polluted water.
كانوا يشربوا منها؟
Did they use to drink from it?
يشربوا، ويسقوا، ويغسلوا، كل شيء، يعني الاعتماد الكلي على
النبعة.
They would drink, water, wash, everything, I mean the total
reliance was on the spring.
كان يصير هون حفلات شي؟ يعني مناسبات اجتماعية، أعياد؟
Did parties or anything happen here? I mean social events,
holidays?
لكان لكان لكان، مناسبات، كنا نحتفل بكل المناسبات،
Of course, of course, of course, occasions, we used to
celebrate all occasions,
مع بعض، كنا متآلفين. يعني كقرية، أسرة وحدة.
together, we were close-knit. I mean, as a village, one
family.
يعني على فكرة، أهل الضيعة كلها بيجمعهم رابط اجتماعي.
I mean, by the way, all the people of the village are united
by a social bond.
أهل الضيعة بشكل عام، يعني هذا متزوج من هذا، هذا قرايب
التاني،
The people of the village in general, I mean this one is
married to this one, this one is a relative of the other,
هذا قرايب التاني، يعني بدك تقول أهل الضيعة كلهم يعني من خليط
مجتمعين مع بعض.
this one is a relative of the other, I mean you could say
all the village people are a mixture gathered together.
المكونات العربية والكردية؟
The Arab and Kurdish components?
من كافة المكونات.
From all components.
وهون كانت تصير يعني خلينا نقول الاحتفالات؟
And here the celebrations, let's say, used to happen?
الاحتفالات مو شرط، مثلاً جوات الضيعة في ساحتين،
The celebrations not necessarily, for example inside the
village there are two squares,
عالم تجتمع هنيكة بالساحات. عرفت كيف؟
people would gather there in the squares. You know?
عالم تيجي مثلاً عالربيع، كانوا يجوا لهون يحتفلوا بالربيع،
عرفت كيف؟
People would come, for example, in the spring, they used to
come here to celebrate spring, you know?
على هـ الخضار، على هـ الطبيعة، على هـ المي، على هـ الكذا.
For this greenery, for this nature, for this water, for this
and that.
الله يعطيك العافية. شكراً إلك.
May God give you health. Thank you.
أهلاً وسهلاً، ع راسي، الله يسلمك. أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, on my head, may God keep you safe. Welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of God and His
blessings.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
أهلاً وسهلاً ومية سلامة. أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome and a hundred greetings. Welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
مية سلامة أهين وسهلين.
A hundred greetings, welcome.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know your name?
عبده عمر جرحو من منطقة عنجارة.
Abdo Omar Jarho from the Anjara area.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
A warm welcome to you.
أهلين وسالمات حبيبي.
Welcome and greetings my dear.
مهجر لهون؟
Displaced to here?
ايه والله.
Yes, by God.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يسلمك حبيبي.
May God keep you safe my dear.
احكيلي إيش في عندك هون؟
Tell me, what do you have here?
والله في الأولاد هون معي عيلتين، وفي معي هالغنمات،
Well, the children are here, I have two families with me,
and I have these sheep,
وفي عندي مغارة حاطط فيها بقرات تحت. ماشي الحال الحمد لله.
and I have a cave down there where I put cows. Things are
fine, thank God.
إيش هي الحياوي؟
What are the livestock?
والله حياوي من الغنم 50، 60 دابة، ومن البقر عشر روس،
Well, livestock, of sheep 50, 60 heads, and of cows ten
heads,
وأولادي عيلتين معهم أنا وأولادي، متزوجين عندي ولدين متزوجين،
and my children are two families with them, me and my
children, married, I have two married sons,
والباقي العيال، هاي الشادرات، هاي الشغل هون عنا.
and the rest are children, these are the tents, this is our
work here.
وين بترعى غنماتك؟
Where do you graze your sheep?
والله عالزيتون، عالزرود، منجيب لهم من الجبل زرود ومنطبلهم،
Well, on the olives, on the foliage, we bring them foliage
from the mountain and chop it for them,
ومنطعميهم الصبح وقعة والمسا وقعة.
and we feed them a meal in the morning and a meal in the
evening.
وضع الناس هون شلون المهجرين؟
How is the situation of the displaced people here?
والله الحمد لله مستورة.
Well, thank God, it's manageable.
شو عم يشتغلوا؟ خلينا نروح نشوف البقرات؟
What are they working on? Let's go see the cows?
تفضل.
Go ahead.
نشوف المغارة؟ هي المغارة قديمة أعتقد.
See the cave? I think this cave is old.
تفضل، مية أهلاً وسهلاً، قديمة كثير.
Go ahead, a hundred welcomes, very old.
كيف وضع المهجرين هون؟ شو بيشتغلوا؟
How is the situation of the displaced people here? What do
they do?
والله المهجرين هون اجا موسم الزيتون، حوشوا زيتون وحووا زيتات
وبركوا،
Well, the displaced people here, the olive season came, they
harvested olives, collected some oil, and sat down,
وعم يستنوا فرج الله لبين ما الله يفرج علينا ونروح ع بلادنا.
and are waiting for God's relief until God relieves us and
we return to our towns.
ايوه، يعني بيشتغلوا في الأراضي؟
I see, so they work in the lands?
في الأراضي، إيه.
In the lands, yes.
هلا هيدي النبعة؟
Now is this the spring?
نعم.
Yes.
هيدي النبعة جاية لهون.
This spring is coming here.
جاية لهون، نعم.
Coming here, yes.
ايوه، وهون هيدي المغارة؟
I see, and here is this cave?
نعم، هي المغارة، وحاطط فيها البقر، تفضل.
Yes, this is the cave, and I put the cows in it, go ahead.
حاطط فيها البقر، ايوه.
You put the cows in it, I see.
وهيدي شجرة جوز؟
And is this a walnut tree?
جوز، ايه. نعم.
Walnut, yes. Yes.
تمام.
Great.
وهذا الوادي.
And this is the valley.
هذا الوادي عندنا هون، نعم.
This is the valley we have here, yes.
تفضل شوي.
Go ahead a bit.
تفضلوا، تفضلوا، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Go ahead, go ahead, welcome.
شرف.
Come in.
تفضلوا.
Go ahead.
شغل اللمبة يا أحمد، يلا شغالها. تفضلوا.
Turn on the lamp Ahmed, come on turn it on. Go ahead.
هلا هيدي المغارة.
Now this is the cave.
نعم.
Yes.
حاطط فيها بقرات؟
You put cows in it?
ايوه، عندي عشر روس بقر حاططهم فيها.
Yes, I have ten head of cattle I put in it.
الله هيك إن شاء الله يمشيك يا رب وينظر بحالكم يا رب.
May God make things go well for you and look after your
condition.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe.
خلينا نطلع.
Let's go up.
مية سلامة.
A hundred greetings.
شرف.
Come in.
تفضلوا، مية أهلاً وسهلاً. أهلاً وسهلين بالشباب.
Go ahead, a hundred welcomes. Welcome to the guys.
هون الـ... يعني البقر والغنم، الماعز، الثروة الحيوانية ماشي
وضعها؟ ماشي حالها؟
Here the... I mean the cows and sheep, goats, livestock, is
their situation going well? Is it fine?
والله الحمد لله، يعني مو متل بلادنا، هون يعني ماشي الحال،
Well thank God, I mean it's not like our towns, here I mean
it's fine,
عم نطعميهم على المعلف والله، وعلف غالي يعني مثل ما بيقولوا،
عم نطعميهم عالمعلف.
we feed them at the trough by God, and fodder is expensive I
mean as they say, we feed them at the trough.
وين بتبيعوا الحليب؟
Where do you sell the milk?
والله بيجوا جماعة من أهل الضيعة هون، والجبنة في متشرواك،
Well, people from the village here come, and the cheese is
shared,
اللي بده كيلوين جبنة واللي بده كيلو جبنة، منبيعها.
whoever wants two kilos of cheese and whoever wants a kilo
of cheese, we sell it.
هلا العام الماضي كان وضع الحيوانات صعب، هالسنة تحسن إن شاء
الله؟
Now last year the animals' situation was difficult, has it
improved this year God willing?
والله بس العلف غالي، تحسن الحمد لله، بس العلف غالي يعني عم
يكسرنا العلف.
Well just the fodder is expensive, it improved thank God,
but the fodder is expensive, I mean the fodder is breaking
us.
عم يكسركم.
Breaking you.
ايه والله.
Yes by God.
ساكنين هلا إنتو هون بخيم؟
Are you living here now in tents?
نعم، نعم.
Yes, yes.
الخيم مناسبة بهالجو؟
Are the tents suitable in this weather?
والله يا أستاذ، برد. حاطين صوبا، فرد خيمة، وفي عندي أربع
خيم،
Well sir, it's cold. We put a heater, one tent, and I have
four tents,
حاطين هالصوبا، ايوه، بس الوضع برد يعني عنا، ومكتف وادي هون،
برد يا أخي.
we put this heater, yes, but the situation is cold I mean
for us, and the valley is adjacent here, it's cold brother.
الله يعينكم.
May God help you.
الله يسلمك يا أستاذ.
May God keep you safe sir.
هلا هيدي شجرة البلوط الكبيرة بالضيعة؟
Now is this the big oak tree in the village?
نعم، نعم، نعم.
Yes, yes, yes.
عمرها كبير كتير؟
Is it very old?
ايه لكان، عمرها فوق الـ 150، 200 سنة.
Yes of course, its age is over 150, 200 years.
150، 200 سنة!
150, 200 years!
كأنه عم تطبخوا عالنار؟
Yes.
It seems you're cooking on the fire?
ايوه، هون نحن منعلّق تفية ومنطبخ عالتفية.
Yes, here we set up a trivet and cook on the trivet.
يلا الله يقويكم والله يعطيكم العافية.
Alright, may God give you strength and health.
الله يعافيك، أهلاً وسهلاً، أبو عبدو مية سلامة والله.
May God give you health, welcome, Abu Abdo a hundred
greetings by God.
شكراً لك. السلام عليكم.
Thank you. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام. مية سلامة والله.
And upon you be peace. A hundred greetings by God.
لمعراتة تاريخ عريق في الحضارة الإنسانية.
Ma'rata has a deep-rooted history in human civilization.
لهذا السبب ربما كانت تسمى قرية الكهوف.
For this reason, it was perhaps called the village of caves.
تعاقبت عليها جميع الحضارات الإنسانية في هذه المنطقة،
All human civilizations in this region succeeded one another
in it,
من الحضارة الآرامية، السريانية، الرومانية، وصولاً حتى العصر
الحالي.
from the Aramean, Syriac, Roman civilizations, all the way
to the current era.
للحديث عن تاريخ معراتة سيكون معنا الأستاذ شيخ عبد الرحمن
حاجي،
To talk about the history of Ma'rata, Mr. Sheikh Abdelrahman
Haji will be with us,
أحد أبناء هذه القرية والمهتم بتاريخها.
one of the sons of this village and someone interested in
its history.
الله يعطيك العافية يا أستاذي.
May God give you health, my sir.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم شباب على راسي.
Welcome guys, on my head.
حياك الله.
May God greet you.
الله يديمكم.
May God sustain you.
الله يكرمك، أستاذي بدي أعرف شقد عمر هالضيعة؟
May God honor you, my sir, I want to know how old is this
village?
بتذكر إنه وعلى معرفتي إنه نحن جينا على هالضيعة من 350 عام.
I remember and to my knowledge that we came to this village
350 years ago.
نعم.
Yes.
نحن، بس عائلتنا 350 عام.
Us, just our family, 350 years.
عائلتكم مين؟
Who is your family?
كانوا يقولوا شندي، بس هلق تفرعنا،
They used to say Shendi, but now we have branched out,
نعم، ايه بيت شندي، من 350 سنة.
yes, the Shendi family, 350 years ago.
وين كنتو؟
Where were you?
كنا ما بعرف، ناس بيقولوا من الشرق جايين، يعني الأكراد من
الشرق جايين لهون،
I don't know where we were, people say coming from the east,
I mean Kurds came from the east to here,
وكان في بيوت، أربع، ست بيوت، سبع بيوت ما بعرف بتذكر،
and there were houses, four, six houses, seven houses, I
don't know I remember,
يعني حسب ما حكولنا إنه كانوا ساكنين هون عدة بيوت يعني.
I mean according to what they told us, there were several
houses living here.
قبل ما يجوا بيت شندي لهون، كان في بيوت كمان؟
Before the Shendi family came here, were there houses too?
لكان!
Of course!
قبلكم؟
Before you?
قبلنا.
Before us.
من وين هدوك كمان؟ كمان أكراد؟
Where were those from too? Also Kurds?
كمان أكراد لكان!
Also Kurds of course!
ايوه.
I see.
هن جددوا هالضيعة وعمروها هني الأكراد.
They renewed this village and built it up, the Kurds.
طيب، تمام. قبل الأكراد كان في شي هون يعني ناس عايشين؟
Okay, great. Before the Kurds, was there anything here, I
mean people living?
كان ناس عايشين، وبعدين تعاقبت عليهم قساوة ظروف الحروب
There were people living, and then the harsh conditions of
wars succeeded upon them,
والكذا والهجرات هاجروا وإجوا وراحوا، من غزوات قديمة،
and such and migrations, they migrated and came and went,
from ancient invasions,
من السريان للرومان لحتى يومنا هذا.
from the Syriacs to the Romans until this day of ours.
يعني أقدم أقدم وجود لمعراتة هي ع الزمن السرياني؟
So the oldest, oldest existence of Ma'rata is from the
Syriac era?
ايه، لأنه اسمها سرياني.
Yes, because its name is Syriac.
آرامي سرياني؟
Aramean Syriac?
لكان آرامي سرياني.
Of course Aramean Syriac.
شو معنات اسمها؟
What does its name mean?
اسمها معراته، عربوها صارت معراتة،
Its name is Ma'rata, they Arabized it and it became Ma'rata,
بس معراته اسمها يعني قرية الكهوف.
but Ma'rata, its name means the village of caves.
قرية الكهوف، هي معناتها.
The village of caves, that's what it means.
قرية الكهوف، نعم.
The village of caves, yes.
في كهوف فعلاً هي؟
Are there actually caves in it?
لكان في كل بيت عليه، عنده مغارة.
Of course, in every house on it, there is a cave.
سكن فيها الإنسان بزمانه؟
People lived in it back in the day?
لكان! كانوا ساكنين فيها بالمغاور بالأول، بالكهوف.
Of course! They used to live in the grottos at first, in the
caves.
طيب، قبل ما أنزل أشوف يعني، نشوف البناء القديم اللي فيها
وبيت الآغا،
Alright, before I go down to see, I mean, we see the old
building in it and the Agha's house,
بيت عبد الله آغا، بدي أعرف يعني المكونات الاجتماعية هون غير
الأكراد مين في؟
Abdullah Agha's house, I want to know, I mean the social
components here, other than the Kurds, who is there?
في أكراد إيزيديين وفي أكراد مسلمين، في عرب؟
There are Yazidi Kurds and there are Muslim Kurds, are there
Arabs?
كلهم إيزيدية كانوا، بعدين أسلموا.
They were all Yazidis, then they became Muslims.
ايوه.
I see.
بالأخير اجو جماعة لعنا هوني، كمان سكنوا معنا لحد الآن.
In the end, a group came to us here, and they also lived
with us until now.
يعني غير الأكراد، العرب كمان سكنوا معنا.
I mean, other than the Kurds, Arabs also lived with us.
العرب، منين اجو العرب؟
Arabs, where did the Arabs come from?
والله من هوني كانوا أصحاب الغنم.
Well, from around here, they were sheep owners.
غنامي؟
Shepherds?
إي غنامي كانوا جايين.
Yes, they were shepherds who came.
وشافوا إنها نهر وطبيعة حلوة وطبيعة جميلة،
And they saw that it has a river, beautiful nature,
هوني عنا بالقرية وسهولة وبجبالها.
here in our village, with its plains and mountains.
ونبعة هوني لحد الآن جارية.
And there is a spring here that is still flowing.
لحد الآن جارية.
Please, go ahead.
It is still flowing until now.
هلأ أنا حسب ما عرفت
Now, according to what I know,
إنه هاد البيت، هاد البيت اللي عند الشجرة،
that this house, this house by the tree,
هي شجرة شو هي، شجرة بلوط؟
Yes.
What tree is this, is it an oak tree?
إيوا، هي بلوط.
Yes, it's an oak.
هاد البيت هو أقدم بيت في القرية، بيت الشيخ زكريا؟
This house is the oldest house in the village, Sheikh
Zakaria's house?
والله في بيت زكريا وبيت هوني قديمة،
Well, there is Zakaria's house and an old house here,
كمان بيت حاج عزت اسمه.
also a house called Haj Izzat's house.
عمو خلينا نروح نشوف البيت.
Uncle, let's go see the house.
إي تفضلوا، شرف.
Yes, please come.
هلأ هاد البيت؟
Now, is this the house?
هاد البيت، هاد هو.
This house, this is it.
هاد واضحة إنه واجهته تاريخية، لكن صاير ترميم يعني شوي.
It's clear that its facade is historical, but there has been
some restoration.
إي طبعاً عملوا له ترميم هنن ولادهم، بعد منهم عملوا ترميم.
Yes, of course, their children restored it, after them they
restored it.
شو هدول اللي على الباب؟
What are those on the door?
هدول للبرْكة للحراس هوني،
These are sitting places for the guards here,
كان حرس يبركوا هوني حرس يبركوا ع الباب.
Guards used to sit here, guards would sit at the door.
تمام. ندخل لجوا؟
Great. Shall we go inside?
شرف.
Please.
شرف شرف سيدي.
Please, go ahead sir.
واضح إنه البيت قديم كتير.
It's clear that the house is very old.
قديم كتير.
Very old.
فعلاً قديم هو وكأنه كان قصر،
It's really old, and it looks like it was a palace,
مصغر شوي في عدة كتل مثلاً.
a mini palace, it has several blocks, for example.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
متل ما بدأنا عفواً بالموضوع،
As we started with the topic, excuse me,
يسلموا إيديك.
Bless your hands.
البيت كان واحد.
the house was one [unit].
كم كتلة كان فيه؟ هلأ أنا شايف هي كتلة وفي كتلة هنيكة.
How many blocks did it have? Now I see this block and there
is a block over there.
وفي لسا لجوا.
And there is still more inside.
لجوا؟
Inside?
في هون كتلة، في وحدة تنتين تلاتة،
There is a block here. There is one, two, three,
وتبع بيت عبد الله أربع ولاد عنده...
and that of Abdullah's house, he has four children...
أيوة، هنيكة لجوا كمان.
Yes, over there inside too.
في بعد منه عمروا، بتعرف إنه كل أخ صار له طرف.
After that they built, you know that every brother got a
side.
طيب أنا في سؤال أستاذي،
Okay, I have a question, sir.
شكل البناء، النمط الهندسي للبناء في معراته،
The shape of the building, the architectural style of the
buildings in Maarrati,
هاد هو الأصلي؟ ولا هاد مميز يعني شيء؟
is this the original? Or is this distinctive?
هاد قديم، هاد قديم.
This is old, this is old.
يعني الصورة الهندسية عندهم كانوا يعمروها
I mean, their architectural image, they used to build it
بهال... يعني البناء هيك.
in this... I mean, building like this.
شرف.
Let's go up.
Please.
خلينا نروح هيك أستاذي.
Let's go this way, sir.
للثورة السورية الكبرى، كان إلها دور مهم.
For the Great Syrian Revolt, it had an important role.
كيف؟ في تاريخ الثورة؟
How? In the history of the revolution?
كانوا هوني إنه عاملين ثورة بشكل مصغرة.
They were here making a revolution in a miniature way.
حتى إجا المرحوم إبراهيم هنانو من جبل الزاوية، من كفر تخاريم
هو.
Until the late Ibrahim Hananu came from Zawiya Mountain, he
is from Kafr Takharim.
إجا لهون وتناسقوا مع بعض تنسيق مع الثورات هوني،
He came here and they coordinated with each other with the
revolutions here,
وكان التنسيق مع حتى الشام ودرعا وسويداء وكذا إلى آخره.
and there was coordination even with Damascus, Daraa,
Suwayda, and so on.
وإجا كان يجي لهون مرة مرتين هيك سمعت.
And he used to come here once or twice, that's what I heard.
إنه كان يجي لهون مشان تنسيق الثورة السورية الكبرى ضد
الفرنسيين.
That he used to come here to coordinate the Great Syrian
Revolt against the French.
طيب تمام، بقي في سؤال بس بدي أعرفه.
Okay great, there's just one question I want to know.
قرأت على إنه محمد نوري باشا،
I read that Muhammad Nuri Pasha,
اللي كان حاكم درعا في العهد العثماني، مر لهون،
who was the ruler of Daraa during the Ottoman era, passed by
here,
وكان إله حادثة شهيرة...
and he had a famous incident...
بأحد الفرنسيين، هاد بأحد الدولة العثمانية.
with one of the French, this was during the Ottoman Empire.
نعم أنا قلت هيك.
Yes, that's what I said.
إي الدولة العثمانية، إجا لهون،
Yes, the Ottoman Empire, he came here.
وحسب ما كانوا يحكوا،
And according to what they used to say,
إنه إله دور كيف إنه يحرّض هالعالم،
that he had a role in how to incite these people,
إنه يا أخي لا تتركوا الدولة العثمانية، بمعنى يعني هيك عامية.
like "Brother, don't leave the Ottoman Empire," meaning in a
colloquial way.
وبعدين شلون ما بعرف، غير هيك ما بعرف هيك سمعت يعني.
And then how, I don't know, other than that I don't know,
this is what I heard.
بس إذا ممكن في عندي قصيدة لمعراتي.
But if possible, I have a poem about Maarrati.
شرف تفضل.
Please, go ahead.
عنوان القصيدة الرقيم.
The title of the poem is Ar-Raqim.
معراتي أم الكهف والرقيم حضارةً،
Maarrati, mother of the cave and Ar-Raqim in civilization,
سراج الهداية والعلم والأدبِ.
the lamp of guidance, science and literature.
زهرة المدائن، زهرة المدائن زاهية الألوانِ،
Flower of the cities, flower of the cities with bright
colors,
أريجها تحيي النفوس والألبابِ.
its fragrance revives souls and minds.
حسام العدالةِ، حسام العدالة وللعقول تغذيةٌ،
The sword of justice, the sword of justice, nourishing the
minds,
ومنبر الحقيقة وفصل الخطابِ.
the pulpit of truth and the decisive speech.
ترفرف في سمائها الطيور،
Birds flutter in its sky,
مغردة بألحان شجية وتطربِ.
singing with melodious tunes and delighting.
سلسبيل ماؤها، تجري بين أضلعها،
Its water is a sweet spring, flowing between its ribs,
لشاربين شفاء وخير شرابِ.
a cure for drinkers and the best of drinks.
تحفها أشجارٌ، تحفها أشجار باسقات كالعروس في خدرها،
Surrounded by trees, surrounded by tall trees like a bride
in her boudoir,
مائلات جنباً إلى جنبِ.
swaying side by side.
بساتينها ألفافاً، وحدائقها غلبا.
Its orchards are dense, and its gardens are lush.
ما شاء الله عليك، يعني جزالة ومسبوكة سباكة الذهب.
Mashallah to you, I mean it's eloquent and cast like gold.
الحمد لله، تسلم.
Praise be to God, thank you.
الله يعطيك العافية. شكراً لك يا أستاذ.
May God give you health. Thank you, sir.
على راسي. هاد وصف القرية الجميلة ومثل ما شفتوها يعني.
You're welcome. This is a description of the beautiful
village, and as you saw it.
الله يكرمك، شكراً لك أستاذ.
May God honor you, thank you sir.
يا على راسي.
You are very welcome.
ضيعة حلوة كتير، استمتعنا بالجولة فيها معكم.
A very beautiful village, we enjoyed the tour with you.
أهم ما استفدناه أنه التعايش هو سمة الشعب السوري،
The most important thing we learned is that coexistence is
the characteristic of the Syrian people,
أينما كان ومن كان هذا السوري،
wherever they are and whoever this Syrian is,
سواءً كان عربياً أو كردياً مسلماً أو إيزيدياً.
whether they are Arab, Kurd, Muslim, or Yazidi.
بدنا منكم تتفاعلوا معنا على صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة،
We want you to interact with us on the channel's Facebook
page,
وأيضاً على معرفاتنا الظاهرة أسفل الشاشة.
and also on our social media handles shown at the bottom of
the screen.
تقترحوا علينا قرى وبلدات ومدن كمواضيع لحلقاتنا القادمة.
Suggest to us villages, towns, and cities as topics for our
upcoming episodes.
رح نودعكم، الأسبوع القادم رح نلتقي بإذن الله تعالى.
We bid you farewell, next week we will meet again, God
willing.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.